This presentation is on Node2Vec, which is a scalable feature learning for networks.
This will be focusing on problems which has been trying to solve,
problems with current approaches and the actual implementation part of the
algorithm, but we'll not be focusing on the,
application side of it. Problem which has been trying to solve is that there's
a graph which is a set of vertices, edges,
and weights. We want to convert it to a low-dimensional space of features.
That maximizes the likelihood of preserving network neighborhoods of nodes.
So it's just a mapping from a graph to a set of features while
preserving network dependencies and,
specifically neighborhood network dependencies.
So for example, if I have a node which is connected to many other
nodes, I would like that information to be captured in the,
feature representation or mapping that I'm using. And why we want to do this
is because most supervised machine learning algorithms require a set of informative,
discriminating, and independent features because only then can we make predictions or
solve anything, basically optimize anything,
on a set of features.
Right, so you require that set of features and you require that mapping from
graph to features. You cannot feed directly a graph into a supervised ML model.
Problems with current approaches is hand engineering is one of the methods that is
done. So, for example, if you know, a protein contact network,
you would probably try to use your domain knowledge to extract features from it,
but that is tedious and not generalizable. A downstream prediction task is accurate,
but time complexity-wise, it's extremely,
huge. The classic, dimensionality reduction algorithms use eigenvectors.
Composition of the data matrix, which is expensive for large real-world networks,
for example, social network have millions and millions of nodes,
and so it will not work with this,
and we have seen that the results that they give are also not very
good on prediction task over networks.
What
Node2Vec was inspired by was from Word2Vec and specifically the Scriptgram methodology
of Word2Vec where we are trying to learn the hidden neural,
so it's a single-layered neural network which converts an input vector which is one-hot
encoded into an output vector which is one-hot encoded, and what we are trying
to do is to,
determine the weights of the hidden layer, and we can convert,
con, control
the dimensions of the vector as well, so we can get a mapping of
the dimension we want mapping from.
The graph to a dimension we want, so over here what was done was,
it was done on a sentence, so a sentence had a context window,
and that context window was,
defined as,
words that are
close by to the particular word that we are looking at, and over there,
we could use the other words in the context window for getting
the hidden layer weights, right?
Over here, in,
in our model of a graph, we do not have that liberty,
because a graph is not a sentence, so we,
do something else to model it as a sentence,
it was inspired by word2vec. Key features are,
it's semi-supervised, it's scalable,
because most of the methods that it uses is parallelizable,
it uses stochastic gradient descent and random walk-of second degree,
which are stochastic approximations, it wants to capture,
we want to capture homophily and structural equivalence,
homophily means that a node U is,
connected to S1, S2, S3, and S4, because they are close by to each
other, U and S6 are also structurally equivalent,
because they have degree 4, and the structure are more or less equal,
topologically,
we want to capture both of these things.
Our objective function is,
probability of next-neighborhood set of U,
given F of U, our objective function is F of U,
we want to maximize this particular summation, why we want to do this is
because, so first of all, we use sampling technique S,
while getting next-neighborhood set of U,
this sampling technique could be BFS over here,
the red arrows, or DFS blue arrows, it could be something wildly different from
that, and that is okay as well,
so we get a next-neighborhood set of U, based on a sampling technique S,
and we want our function to get as close to that as possible,
we use logarithmic to prevent underflow errors,
there are two approximations,
one of them is that these are conditionally,
independence, there's conditional independence in the probabilities of the neighbors
of U, in the neighbors belonging to the next-neighborhood set of U,
and there is a symmetry requirement,
which enables a decomposition into,
this using the softmax function,
ZU is
extremely,
difficult to calculate, so we use negative weights,
so instead of, doing this for every node and every,
ne-ne-node in the next-neighborhood set, we do it for only few nodes,
a small subset of the weights, right,
we still have positive context words, but,
we do not update the
weights for every word. So over here we use a second-order random walk,
which is basically that if we are given a node V and it came
from T, we would have probabilities assigned to it going back to T,
probability of going to a node which it is directly connected to,
and which it is connected to via two nodes.
So if the distance between them is two, there would be a probability of
one by Q, where Q is something we can control.
If it came from T, where there will be one by P,
we can control P, right? Z is a normalization constant,
pi is the weight, and the alpha parameter, alpha parameter
is something that we can control. It's an added term. It's an added term
for introducing bias in the random walk because we can control the bias by
tuning the hyperparameters,
The actual algorithm, I think I've gone through most of it.
Limitations, it does not differentiate between the relation types.
For example, if I am doing a movie,
sequence as a particular graph, there
are various kinds of relationships in that movie.
A husband, wife, a boyfriend, girlfriend,
a son, daughter, etc.
so we, Node2Vec takes a graph as a set of V,
E, and W, that's it.
It does not consider features within any of those,
V, E, or W, right?
it depends only on network topology. It's a transductive node embedding algorithm,
means that it needs the entire graph to be available to learn the node
embeddings. We cannot run it on a subset of subgraphs.